Welcome back and today we going to cover
distributeduling part two. So if you
have not seen the part one where we have
covered like what is scheduuler, how it
internally works, we have also seen how
threadpull executor works internally. So
we have already seen in depth of it all
its method like schedule method which
runs only one schedule at schedule at
fixed rate with example schedule with
fixed delay with a proper example and
also the internal functionality.
So that's the prerequisite for this
video. Okay. So a spring boot does not
perform any magic. it internally make
use of schedule threadpool executor
itself. Okay. So in other words, it's
just a wrapper above schedule threadpool
executor. So let's see that how to
configure theuling in spring boot. So
the first step is enable theuling. Okay.
So in your spring boot application you
have to add this add the enablesuling
annotation because after this only all
the scheduleuler related beans will get
loaded. Okay. And after this only it
will be have the capability to scan for
at the rate scheduled annotations.
Without this theuling will not even
work. It doesn't even know. Okay, it
won't even scan the scheduled
annotation.
So that is a very basic step. After that
we just need to see what type of
shoulduling we want whe the fixed rate,
fixed delay, one-time shoulduling and
chron job. Now if you have already seen
the part one we have already know in
depth of how this three works. We have
already have like schedule method
schedule with
fixed delay method and schedule at fixed
rate method. So internally all these
types in spring boot actually use what
we have already seen in uh schedule
threadpool executor methods. Okay. So
only thing here new is like chron job.
So let's see that the fixed rate. So how
to use the fixed rate in spring boot. So
we create a class. Okay. And I have
annotated with at the rate component.
Now this is the method. So this method
consider this as a task which need to be
scheduled. Okay. Now currently I am
using fixed rate. Okay. I am not
explaining how fixed rate works because
in the part one itself we have seen it
and this fixed rate is equivalent to
schedule at fixed rate. What in the part
one we have seen how it works. We have
already seen the example. Okay. So here
it just you can say that wrap in spring
it's just a wrapper above it and we can
use it like add the rate schedule
initial delay is this 3 second and the
delay after that which we wanted to
maintain is 5 second okay so these are
here in milliseconds
and internally here I have used see
fixed rate so internally it make use of
schedule at fixed rate method only
so Somewhere you will also see that many
engineers don't even write a spring
delay. So if you don't write it like
this then default is zero means start as
soon as the job is submitted.
Okay. Otherwise if you here I have put 3
seconds. So means once the job is
submitted after 3 second itself
after 3 second itself the task will get
started.
Okay. And if you see the output you can
see that the application started at 38
then it the one is 41. So it maintain an
initial delay of 3 second after that
every 5 seconds. So you remember from
the previous video fixed rate what's the
formula to find the next execution time?
previous start time
plus the delay which we wanted. So
previous start time let's say 41
plus delay we have set is five. So next
it should run 46.
Then after 46 once it get executed at 46
the next time it has to find the next
execution time. So previous start time.
So 46 + 5 likewise 51 56 like this it
keeps on going.
Okay. So if you have any doubt with this
method schedule should fix rate how this
is working kindly check out the part one
of this it will get super clear.
The second is fixed delay. Again we have
covered the functionality in the part
one with this method schedule with fixed
delay. So spring boot is provide no
other functionality. just a wrapper
above this method you can say schedule
with fixed delay and here I have just
put an annotation at the schedule so
this is my let's say task which I want
to run I put at the schedule initial
delay whatever I want to provide and fix
delay is 5 seconds so it just like use
this method so here just for testing
purpose I have recorded the start time
and just make the thread sleep for 3
seconds recorded the end time and just
printing. So just if you see the outcome
so you remember from the first video
like for fixed delay
what's the formula for calculating the
next execution time is like previous
task finish time not start time finish
time
plus delay.
So here when task is submitted what's
the initial delay is 1 second. So
application started at uh here it is at
31. So it is after 1 second delay you
can say that 32 it started. So at 32 it
started I have put sleep. Okay 3 seconds
sleep. So when it got finished it got
finished at 35. So what should be the
next? So
here in the fixed delay it's repetitive.
We need to put the task again back to
the queue but with a new execution time.
So new execution time would be previous
task finish time. So when it is finished
35 plus the delay delay we have set is
five. So it should run on next 40. So it
run at 40. Let's say it finished at 43.
So what should be the next finish time?
Previous finish time 43 plus the delay
48. Likewise it keeps on going.
Okay. So again we have already covered
this. So that's why I'm going a little
bit fast over here. Now one is onetime
that is also equivalent to schedule
method in the part one which we have
covered. Okay. So here means we have to
run the job only one time only one time.
So this is my task I put at the
schedule. Now initial delay so when you
need to start so they're the same thing
the task and the delay. Okay. So here
let's say if you want to start it
immediately just put zero. If you want
to start let's say after 2 seconds just
put here. So all this is in
milliseconds.
Okay. But here initial delay is
mandatory. You can't have you if you
don't define it here you will get an
exception. So you should define initial
delay in case of one timeuling. Okay.
But if you are using fixed delay or
fixed rate if you don't add initial
delay by default it will take zero.
Okay. But only in case of one time
shoulduling
you have to specifically add the initial
delay.
So in this case what would happen is
after an initial delay of 2 second job
will start and it will get executed only
one time.
Cool. The main thing is now chron job
which is new. Okay. So now let's see it
clearly.
What it says chron job is repeated one
timeuling repeated. So it's also a
repeat of
whatever the clock time we give. So it
based on wall clock time. This is very
important. So and also very confusing
too. What does wall clock time means? So
in like in a wall clock time we have
like seconds, minute, hour. Okay, the
same way it follows. So example of wall
clock time. Let's see the example
clearly because this is where many
confusion happen.
Let's say current time is 10:14
and what we wanted is every 3 minutes we
need to run the task every 3 minutes. So
with fixed rate what would what would
have happened? So now let's say the
first pick would happen 10:14 if it
let's say if our initial delay is zero
means as soon as the current time is
10:14 as soon as the job is submitted it
got picked up. So first pick is this.
Now the next execution at what time? So
we want every 3 minutes. So how what is
the execution time formula? Next
execution time calculation formula in
fixed rate is previous
start time previous start time. So it is
started on 10:14
plus interval we want three. So at 10:17
it will run next execution time would be
previous start time. So 1017 it started
plus 3 1020.
Okay. So this is how generally fixed
rate might have worked.
Fixed delay. How this scenario works in
fixed delay is that
let's say first pick started at 10:14
but finished at 10:15. So when you have
to put back again into the queue with
the new execution time it would be like
previous execution end time. So end time
is 10:15 + 3 10810. Now let's say uh
when it got picked at 10:18 complete at
10:19. So next execution time is
previous finish time 1019 + 3 10:22
likewise
but in case of chron it follows wall
clock time. So when we are saying every
3 minutes so in the clockwise it's like
0 3 6 9 12 15 18 21 likewise. Okay. So
currently it's 10 for 10. So currently
it's 10 for 10. Okay. So now when so if
task get completed on time let's say
next run would be on 10:15
okay so it follows wall clock time 0 3 6
so every 3 minutes right 0 3 6 9 12 till
you can say that uh like within 60 it
goes so 59 0 to 59 so 0 to 59 it goes so
likewise 333 minutes gap it will go
so in this case if it is uh 104 A task
get executed and if it get completed
within time then the next run it would
be at 15 after that 18 after that 21
likewise but if the task takes longer
let's say at 10:14 is started and
completed at 10:16
then what would be the nextuling time
you can see from this itself the next at
16 it get completed right so next
shoulduling time would be at 8:10
okay so that's the wall clock time
scenario
the things will get more clear with more
further examples but that's the one
thing it's a repeated job only repeated
one time scheduleuler but based on wall
clock time
okay so this is just the same thing
repeated like uh next execution time
compute it and schedule it back to the
queue like the same thing
okay again one more example I am going
one more example because see this is
important before I goes to the
expression which is very important in
the chron job. Okay. So there should not
be any doubt with like how chron jobs uh
likeuling works. Okay. Consider this
scenario. The requirement is that every
10 minutes
okay micron job should start or should
work. The task is started at 10
10 a.m. you can consider and it runs for
25 minutes. Okay. So what is your
expected chron times? Expected is that
after 10 it should again wake up at
10:10 then 10:20 then 10:30 likewise.
Okay. But what happened is when it
picked at 10 it takes long time and it
take it took 25 minutes. So at 10 what
actually happen is at 10 my task start
at 10:10 you can say that chron time
occurs but missed as task is still
running. See in the part one also I told
we have only one task which is present
into the queue. Okay. So when the task
is running
it get receded only when it get
completed. It's not possible that this
task is running and let's say the next
timer happens and some other thread
again start this task. Not possible.
Only have one task, one object.
Currently it's in running state. Once it
get finished, it again put back to the
queue with the new execution time. So
currently 10 task start but at 10:10
generally expectation is it should get
run but currently task is running 10:20
expectation is is cron should wake up
but currently my task is running so
nothing will happen now 10:25 my task
got finished okay at 10:25 my task is
finished now it has to be recued back
with new execution time so how it will
compute new execution time. Okay. So
what chron says that every 10 minute so
it follows clock time 0 10 20 30
till 50. Okay. So after because 59 60 is
not counted 0 to 59. So these are the
minutes.
So now here if you say 10 the job runs
the next time is that 1010 10
already missed. We are at 1025. So it
missed. Then after that 20 20 is also
missed. We are at 25. After that 30 yes
it's a future currently is this. So our
delay is 5 minutes. And now like
previous in the part one for five
minutes it will go into the time wait
state and after the timer complete the
thread will wake up by the OS thread and
at 10:30 it will pick the task.
So I hope chron job functionality on the
uh like wall clock scenario it's clear
and it how to use it it's very simple
that uh the same thing you have a class
annotated with add the component this
method is generally considered as task
and here I have put add the schedule
like and inside this we have chrome
equals to chron expression this is
important the chron expression so Here
what I have said is job runs every 3
seconds. So we need to understand this
expression. Okay. So you can see the
output that it run every 3 seconds. So
12 15 18 214. So every 3 seconds I told
to run. Okay.
So like we need to understand this chron
expression better and with if that got
clear then I think chron job is nothing
because in the part one we have already
know the internal how it worked. So the
same thing like we know what thread
might be doing, how thread get to sleep
for a specific time, how they got
invoked up, how the delayed Q is
maintained. So we already know that. So
it's a piece of cake for us. Only thing
is we need to understand the syntax.
So here in the chron expression syntax,
it has six part separated by a space.
Second, minute are day of the month.
Okay, month day of the week. So second
is 0 to 59.
Minute is 0 to 59.
R is 0 to 23. This is like a normal wall
clock. Okay. Starting from zero like 11
59. It started from 11 0 to 1159 like
the normal thing. the same thing. Now
the day of the month 1 to 31st.
Okay, day of the month is either 1 to
31st. We can define month either you can
give 1 2 3 or 12 or you can also give
Jan, J and D C three words capital
day of the week. Day of the week is like
0 to 7. You can give or sun to set like
three words capitals m o n t u e wed d
likewise. Now here you might see that
hey 0 to 7 is 8 but we have only 7 days
in a week. So here 0 is also Sunday 7 is
also Sunday
1 2 3 4 5 6 it's like Monday Tuesday
Thursday Friday but 0 and 7 is Sunday.
Okay. So this is a very basic like uh
syntax. Now it also has certain special
characters. We need to see that. But
then we will see some practical
examples.
The first is asteris. Astress means
every. Okay. So let's say we have the
six parts. Now in whichever part you put
estress. So this is like second then you
have minute. If you put estress in a
minute, what does how do we read it?
like
every minute. So estrus means every
every minute. If you put estrogen
second, every second. Okay. If you put
estrog in r, it's like every r. This is
how we read it. Okay. So estster means
every.
Then we have comma. You can say it's a
considered as list used to specify
multiple values. Okay. Like 0, 20 in the
second field. So in the second field I
put 0, 20. So a star. So let's say
something else. So what I will say that
for every minute
in the second is 0 and 20th second only.
0 and 20th second task runs. Okay? Not
every second only 0 and 20.
If I put 9, 15 in the hour. So this is
second, this is minute, this is hour. If
I put 9, 15, what does it mean?
uh here in the means that the job need
to run 9 a.m. or 15 means 3 p.m. So it's
a list
then we have hyphen which is known as
range. So in the r 2 minute r if I put 9
- 15 means every hour between 900 a.m.
to 300 p.m. every hour. So between this
including job need to be run.
So every hour from 9:00 a.m. to 3 p.m.
that is range.
Then we have a slash. It is used to
specify intervals.
So
like here you can say that we have a
start and step.
For example 4/10
let's say in the second field. What does
it mean? Job need to be executed at 4th
second then keep adding 10 second. So
it's just like an step over like add on
to this. So after 4 second you need to
keep add 10 10 10 seconds. So 4 14 24 34
44 54. Okay. So 0 to 59 is the seconds
right? So 4 by 10 in the second field
means start at four after that 10 10 10
uh interval we need to maintain
/ash by 10 in the second field means
start from zero zero then plus 10 10 20
30 40 50 likewise
then we have L. L means last and it is
only allowed in day of the month and day
of the week.
Okay. So day of the month, L in the day
of the month means last day of the
month. Last day if it's a February
month, the last day could be the 28 29.
It it takes out into the calculation. If
it's April, it's 30. If it's December,
it is 31. So last day of the month
and L in the day of the week is like
last day of the week. Uh last occurrence
of the given weekday in the month. Okay.
So now let's say you have given Friday
last. So it's syntax is day and l. Okay.
So day is like like if you have put
Friday L. So last Friday of the month.
If you have put Monday Last Monday of
the month.
Okay. Then there is something called
question mark. It is used to tell that
ignore this field. Okay. also allowed
only in these two field day of the month
and day of the week. So generally its
main purpose is to remove the ambiguity.
So see understand this how ambiguity can
come. Let's say if I have used this
expression how you will read.
So is it every day? See second [snorts]
this is second this is minute this is
hour. Okay. Day of the month. A star.
Every day. Okay. This what a star means.
Every day. Day of the month. Every day.
But here I am saying day of the week
Monday. So now it's confusing. Are you
trying to say every day you should run
or every month Monday? Every Monday I
you want to run. So it's become
ambiguity. So what to do in that case?
We can make use of question mark. Hey,
when I want every Monday, ignore this
field. Day of the month. I don't want to
put a star or I don't want to put a day
itself. I just want to put every Monday.
So day, you can ignore it. Question
mark.
Okay.
So these are some practical examples you
can practice it with it.
So first is every 5 seconds. So every 5
seconds is like if you see this syntax
on the second part I put estster five
and everything else like uh every so
like it would run on zero then five then
10 then 15 likewise if you have like
every 4 minute job need to be run so in
the minute part I have put estress 4. So
currently what happen is my job would
start at
0 then 4 then 8 then 12 likewise
then like every day at 11:15 a.m. Okay.
So here I have put this is r I have put
11 this is minute and seconds I have
specifically put zero okay and the day
of the month I have put everywhere
start. So it's like every day it will
run this job will get executed every day
at 11:15 a.m.
Every weekday at 9:00 a.m. Every weekday
let's say weekday is Monday to Friday.
So in the day of the week I have put
specifically Monday to Friday only. Okay
every months this week. So I have put a
star
day of the month whether it's 1 to I
don't care. So that's why I put question
mark. Okay please ignore here I'm
telling ignore this. I want to run
Monday Friday no matter what the day is
whether it's the 5th or 6th or 7th
whatever the date is I don't care day
matter. Okay. And 9:00 a.m. So this is
9:00 a.m.
every Sunday at midnight. Sunday at
midnight. So day I am talking about this
Sunday. I don't care about what's the
date. So that's why I put question mark
every month. So I put asteris midnight
is 0000. Start from here
runs at midnight on first day of every
month. Every month's first day. Okay.
Midnight. So what I have told is the
date I'm interested in like date
one. Now the day I don't care whether on
the first it's Monday or Sunday I don't
care that's why I put koshima okay month
every month and midnight I want it zero
last day of every month at midnight so
if this is the requirement so midnight
so this is the hour minute second for
the midnight okay and then we are saying
is day last date okay uh so it's like a
last date this is the last date.
So if the month last date is 29 or uh 30
or 31 or 28 so pick whatever the last
date of a month is for every month pick
a last date I don't care about the day
whether the last date is Sunday Monday I
don't care so this is just practical
example of chron jobs like you can
practice it more and you can try it out
but if you understood the part one the
internal is clear and then this is all
about syntax.
I hope uh this is clear. If there is any
doubt let me know we can discuss further
into the comment section. Bye.